Good morning. Today's דף daf is קט"ז, kuf-tet-zayin, which is 116. And
we pick up five lines from the top, מאן
תנא, man tanna, one, two, three, yeah, five lines from the top,
middle line. We have been discussing that if a ספר תורה sefer
Torah has 85 letters scattered throughout it, then it is considered to
still have the status of ספר תורה, sefer Torah, would be saved
on שבת, Shabbat, learned from this idea of ויהי בנסוע הארון Vayehi
Binsoa Ha'aron being a little mini ספר תורה. sefer Torah. And now
the גמרא Gemara continues, מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי? man tanna de-palig
alei de-Rabbi? Who argues on רבי Rabbi that this is not the
idea of the ויהי בנסוע, vayehi binsoa, it's not this idea of
its own being its own ספר תורה? sefer Torah? So who is
the תנא tanna that argues? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל הוא, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel hu, member of his family, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, baraita, רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר עתידה פרשה זו שתעקר מכאן ותכתב במקומה. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, atida parsha zo she-te'akeir mikan ve-tikatev bimkoma. Eventually
this פסוק pasuk will be this פרשה parsha will be taken out
of here, eventually like in ימות המשיח yemos hamashiach and put in
the right place where it belongs, which is not in פרשת, parshas,
you know, not in נשא Naso but in במדבר Bamidbar where it
originally lays out the דגלים degalim and the movement, that's where it'll
say ויהי בנסוע הארון. Vayehi Binsoa Ha'aron. Okay, ולמה כתבה כאן? ve-lama
ketava kan? Why was it written here? כדי להפסיק בין פורענות ראשונה
לפורענות שנייה. kedei lehafzik bein puraniyot rishona le-puraniyot sheniya. Because when it's
after the whole beginning of במדבר Bamidbar where it talks about dividing
into camps and now it's about to talk about them moving out,
you want to distinguish between the early פורענות, puraniyot, the early like
misdeeds and punishments and the later ones. So we're going to see.
פורענות שנייה מאי היא? puraniyot sheniya mai hi? So the later ones,
it's clear because right after it says ויהי בנסוע הארון, vayehi binsoa
ha'aron, it says, ויהי העם כמתאננים, vayehi ha'am kemit'onenim, that the people
began to complain, right? And they basically were saying, you know, we
you know lacked food and water and were complaining to משה Moshe
like we already started in this week's פרשה. parsha. So that's very
clear what the second ones are. But what's the first one? Actually
it's specifically around the meat and that's the whole story about the
שלו. slav. So פורענות ראשונה, puraniyot rishona, so what was the first
one? ויסעו מהר ה'. vayisu me-har Hashem. When it says right before
ויהי בנסוע הארון vayehi binsoa ha'aron is it says that they traveled
from the mountain of God, right? ואמר רבי חמא ve-amar Rabbi Hama
by the way, you know, it's worth noting that from יתרו Yitro
next
week's
פרשה parsha
till נשא, Naso, it's all taking place at the foot of הר
סיני. Har Sinai. They arrive at הר סיני, Har Sinai, they get
the תורה, Torah, they do the חטא העגל, cheit ha-egel, they get
the commandment of the משכן, Mishkan, that takes us to the end
of שמות. Shemot. Then they get the commandments of the sacrifices and
then all of the related things and that's all of ויקרא. Vayikra.
And then במדבר Bamidbar they start dividing up into the camp and
moving forward. So until then they were all at the foot of
הר סיני. Har Sinai. So and it says they traveled from the
mountain of God, ויסעו מהר ה', vayisu me-har Hashem, ואמר רבי חמא
בר חנינא ve-amar Rabbi Hama bar Hanina שסרו מאחרי ה', she-saru me-acharei
Hashem, that they turned from away from God. So that already indicates
a leaving of God. Now what does it mean? Where do what
does that mean? In what way did they do that? So if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י? Rashi? מאחרי
ה', me-acharei Hashem, about ten lines down on the narrow lines, בתוך
ג' ימים למסעם התאוו האספסוף תאוה. betoch gimel yamim le-massa'am hit'avu ha-asafsaf
ta'ava. לדרש על הפסוק כדי לומר ברוך ה'. li-drosh al ha-pasuk kedei
leimor baruch Hashem. So רש"י Rashi just says it
means that it's just a it's just like presaging the next discussion
about the next story about them desiring meat. So but since it
alludes to it as soon as they left the mountain of God,
they already started, you know, desiring and complaining or whatever and then
it reached the, you know, the sort of the culmination when it
says that they then demanded meat, למה זה יצאנו ממצרים, lama zeh
yatzanu mi-Mitzrayim, but that process already began earlier. So to break that
up. That's why רש"י Rashi says it was really one process that
began as soon as they left
הר סיני. Har Sinai. תוספות Tosafot says פורענות ראשונה, puraniyot rishona, so
he says,
פירש בקונטרס דמאז התחילו לשאול בשר, pirish bakuntres she-me-az hitchilu lishol basar,
ואמר ר"י דאין לו כן, ve-amar Ri de-ein lo ken, אלא פורענות
ראשונה כדאמר במדרש ויסעו שנסעו מהר סיני דרך שלשת ימים כתינוק היוצא
מבית הספר, ela puraniyot rishona ki-de-amar bamidrash, vayisu she-nas'u me-Har Sinai derech
sheloshet yamim, ke-tinok ha-yotzei mi-beit ha-sefer, like you know, when school is
out, you know, the kids run out of school, they're thrilled to
just be finally leaving, you know, שבורח לו והולך לו, she-boreach lo
ve-holech lo, that they, you know, ran out as fast as they
could get out of school. כך היו בורחים מהר סיני דרך שלשת
ימים לפי שלמדו הרבה תורה בסיני. kach hayu borchim me-Har Sinai derech
sheloshet yamim, le-fi she-lamdu harbe Torah be-Sinai.
So they learned a lot of תורה Torah at סיני Sinai and
now it was time they needed a little to get a little
free from all of that. So okay. So that anyway and that's
the and that's the breaking up of ויהי בנסוע הארון, vayehi binsoa
ha'aron, which is a more positive statement, right? קומה ה' ויפוצו איביך,
kuma Hashem ve-yafutzu oyvecha, right the sense that even within the movement
it comes with a sense about following God and being led by
God and not running away from God. So actually that also a
little bit works in terms of how the role of ויהי בנסוע
vayehi binsoa is a little bit breaking that up. Yes.
So but what I don't understand is, I mean, if it weren't
for this מדרש, midrash, that would have taken it all to have
been positive because you know talking about יתרו, Yitro, you know, תלך
עמנו te-lech imanu and this and then they went on their way.
Right. So they're creating a problem and then well part of it
is so they're creating a problem, an artificially creating a problem in
order to come up with an artificial solution. And then secondly, the
two other פורענויות Puraniyot add to that. There's the מתאוננים Mitonim and
then that stopped and then there's the אספסוף אשר בקרבו התאוו תאוה.
Asafsuf Asher Bekirbo Hitavu Ta'avah. You could say that that's the third
one. So then how is this even helping putting this here because
then there is a פורענות Puraniut second and a פורענות Puraniut third,
both of which are explicit. So if anything I would have put
it between the second and the third which are explicit, so it
could be in between.
So I don't think they're creating a problem. I think they're responding
to two things. Number one is the nuns that precede and follow
and that somehow setting that out that needs to be explained why
is this being set out of everything else. And number two, they
did have a sense that this was not exactly the most appropriate
place for this פרשה. Parsha. It would have fit better in במדבר
Bamidbar when it discusses, you know, when it more lays out the
basic means of travel and moving and how the camps break up
and so on. So I think both of those were things that
they were responding to. Now whether the answer is sufficient or not
is a good question. What for example does the answer of ספר
תורה בפני עצמו Sefer Torah Bifnei Atzmo mean? It's itself a question.
And this issue I think that the point to answer your point,
yes, I mean they're always complaining on a non on a continuing
basis starting in like last, you know, with the פרשה Parsha that
we read yesterday. But I think the point here is that is
that
that sense of like that immediacy after leaving הר סיני. Har Sinai.
That you know it's very disturbing that idea that the second they
leave all of a sudden you know that's it they fall right
back into their old pattern. So to take a moment for pause
and to allow that to have like they moved, you pause, you
speak about ויהי בנסוע Vayehi Binsoa and then this happened like at
a separate stage. It's not like a continuous process from the moment
they left הר סיני, Har Sinai, that I think is a way
of understanding it. Obviously yes there's tons of פורענויות Puraniyot and they're
constantly being juxtaposed one to the other which is a very good
point.
Yes. According to רש"י, Rashi, the Torah is full of things that
are out of sequence.
That's true also. Right, that's true also. רש"י Rashi never has a
problem with saying אין מוקדם ומאוחר בתורה. Ein Mukdam Umuchar BaTorah. Yeah.
Okay, so all that is very good. I actually did have like
I said something I wrote about this ספר תורה בפני עצמו Sefer
Torah Bifnei Atzmo but I don't remember it so I'm anyway I'll
find it, I'll send it out to you. Alright so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
היכן מקומה Heichan mekomah where should it belong? So אמר רב אשי
Amar Rav Ashi בדגלים. Bidgalim. By בדגלים, Bidgalim, by the actual setting
up of the various camps and how they you know the basic
description of how they would move which occurred a פרשה Parsha earlier
in במדבר. Bamidbar. Okay, so that's the end of that discussion about
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah with eighty five let that has eighty
five letters remaining. Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
You didn't finish answering it though because we said...
Yeah well there's a debate whether it means eighty five in one
place or spread out.
So no answer right?
No answer right, it's a debate. איבעיא להו. Ibayu lehu. So now
they're moving on. So they've raised this question about written down ברכות
Brachot and קמיעין Kemiyot and things that were written
that by the way and
and various things that are written in other languages or other scripts
or maybe even in other inks that there are opinions that not
only do you not read those things because there's a concern but
you actually can even allow them to burn or there was even
one story where somebody actually actively buried it under you know under
the you know רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel buried it under you know
under the row of bricks. So it's all so very like you
know shocking statements even in things that have שם השם Shem Hashem
in them, shocking statements which really as I said point out to
this very strong line they wanted to keep between what was written
the you know scripture and everything else which was part of their
oral culture and they didn't want to blur those lines which doesn't
apply nowadays as תוספות Tosafos we said yesterday says that nowadays where
we write everything down and we're given an allowance עת לעשות להשם
הפרו תורתך Eis la'asos lashem heferu torasecha
then of course all that changes. But at a time where they
wanted to make it very clear what was scripture and what wasn't,
things that should not have been in that category had to be
put in גניזה Geniza and maybe you would even allow them to
burn. So that was quite shocking. I would say that some ראשונים
Rishonim do want to suggest that when it says you let the
שם השם Shem Hashems burn from like the ברכות Brachot and other
types of things we weren't talking about literally שם השם, Shem Hashem,
we're talking about like things they do now like a יי Yud-Yud
or something to symbolize שם השם. Shem Hashem. It didn't sound that
way but some are really so bothered by that idea that that's
what they say. Okay so that's about various things and then even
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah itself at what stage assuming it doesn't
have שם השם Shem Hashem does it still retain קדושת ספר תורה
Kedushat Sefer Torah that you would save it, that was this discussion
of eighty five letters. So now we move on to other types
of areas
where you would where the question about to what degree they have
this קדושה Kedusha to be saved. So here's the גמרא's Gemara question.
איבעיא להו, Ibayu lehu, they raised the question: הגליונים של ספר תורה,
Hagilyonim shel sefer Torah, what about the margins, the white space in
a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? מצילים אותן מפני הדליקה או אין מצילים
אותן מפני הדליקה? Matzilim otan mipnei hadleka o ein matzilim otan mipnei
hadleka? Would that be saved? It doesn't have writing on it, just
the parchment that was part of it. Throw it away? Well we'll
talk about it. So there are various possibilities. There's the stuff that
was intentionally left as a margin. You know anybody that's ever you
know played around with their margins in Word knows you know what's
the top margin, bottom margin, the right, the left. So you would
have white space at the beginning of the scroll, you'd have blank
margin at the end of the scroll, you obviously have a margin
at the top and a margin at the bottom, you have space
between the columns, all of that is גליונים. Gilyonim. But רש"י Rashi
says it's also assuming that what's included is if it's if the
place where the writing is on gets scraped off. scraped away and
you're left with blank parchment underneath, that also's considered גיליונים. gilyonim. So
all of that stuff, does it retain its קדושה? kedusha?
Okay, so that's the question, means from margins not having writing.
So well, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So it
says like this, you'll see, the— I mean, the obvious questions you
would ask are going to come up in the
גמרא. Gemara. What? Right, or a fragment, exactly. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. ספר
תורה שבלה, Sefer Torah shebalah, if a ספר תורה Sefer Torah wore
out, which basically the גמרא— Gemara oh, well let's read it. אם
יש בו לקבץ שמונים וחמש אותיות כגון פרשת ויהי בנסוע הארון מצילים.
Im yesh bo lekabet shemonim vechamisha otiyot kegon parshat vayehi binsua ha'aron
matzilin. If you can— if there are 85 letters spread out throughout
it, you can save it, it still has קדושת ספר תורה, kedushat
Sefer Torah, ואם לאו אין מצילים, ve'im lav ein matzilin, if not,
you don't save it. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, v'amai, why
even if it has fewer than 85 letters, תיפוק ליה משום גיליון
דידיה, teipokei lei mishum gilyon didei, how about even all the places
the letters have been scraped away from, you have the parchment underneath?
So, who cares if there are— if the parchment of a ספר
תורה Sefer Torah needs to be saved even with fewer than 84
letters, you have the parchment on which these letters were written. So
the גמרא Gemara says: משום גיליון דידיה? Mishum gilyon didei? So it
says בלה שאני. balah shani. No, worn out is different because it
assumes what worn out means is not that the letters got scraped
away, it means that actually the parchment itself, you know, dissolved. The
parchment itself sort of fell apart. So you actually don't even have
parchment underneath. So therefore you don't even have that reality of any
remaining parchment. So okay. So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta
shema, fine, let's get a better example. ספר תורה שנמחק, Sefer Torah
shenimchak, this ברייתא brayta is exactly the same as the previous one
except instead of the word שבלה, shebalah, which could mean that the
actual parchment broke away, it says שנמחק. shenimchak. The writing was erased,
which means the parchment underneath remained. אם יש בו לקבץ שמונים וחמש
אותיות כגון פרשת ויהי בנסוע הארון מצילים. Im yesh bo lekabet shemonim
vechamisha otiyot kegon parshat vayehi binsua ha'aron matzilin. If it has 85
letters like in the פרשה parsha ויהי בנסוע הארון, vayehi binsua ha'aron,
מצילים, matzilin, then you would save it. ואם לאו אין מצילים, ve'im
lav ein matzilin, if not you would not save it. ואמאי, v'amai,
why even if it has fewer than 85, תיפוק ליה משום גיליון
דידיה? teipokei lei mishum gilyon didei? How about the fact that the
parchment itself underneath where the letters had been written? If you say
the parchment is— has קדושה kedusha and should be saved, so why
don't you save it? So the גמרא Gemara says: מקום הכתב לא
קמיבעיא ליה. Mekom haksav lo kamiba'ei lei. No, I'm not asking about
the place where writing used to be. דכי קדוש, Dechi kadosh, because
that, when that place, when the place on which the writing was
done was sanctified, אגב כתב הוא דקדוש. agav ksav hu dekadosh. The
reason the parchment on which you would write was sanctified was for
the sake of having the writing on it. אזל כתב, Azal ksav,
as soon as the writing goes away, אזלה ליה קדושתיה, azla lei
kedushatei, the קדושה kedusha goes away. I know, you would have thought
that the place that the writing was actually on got more seriously
sanctified than just the margins. But that's the גמרא Gemara is trying
to— is saying this so it— so we still have a live
question. So the part that was made for the sake of the
writing, its whole status is dependent on the presence of the writing.
And when the writing goes away, its status goes away. כי קמיבעיא
ליה, Ki kamiba'ei lei, my question is the part that was intentionally
left blank. That maybe its status is even in its blank state.
שמעלה ושמטה, Shema'alah veshematah, the margin above, the margin below. שבין פרשה
לפרשה, Shebein parsha leparsha, the space between פרשיות, parshiyot, like if you
have a סתומה, stumah, you know, and not a— or if you
have a פתוחה, ptucha, when one פרשה parsha ends, you need to
have whitespace till the end of the paragraph, or you have a
certain section of whitespace if it's a סתומה stumah and then the
next paragraph begins. So that's whitespace there. שבין דף לדף, Shebein daf
ledaf, between one, you know,
column and the next column. שבתחילת הספר ושבסוף הספר, Shebitchilat hasefer veshebesof
hasefer, the stuff right before בראשית, Bereishit, the stuff after the end
of דברים, Devarim, you have a whole, you know, blank segment. So
all of that is intentionally left blank. So therefore its קדושה, kedusha,
its status is— is made for even with no writing on it.
So maybe you would save that even without any writing. That itself
has קדושת ספר תורה. kedushat Sefer Torah.
No, even not.
Just the fact that that was made and once it was part
of a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. The basic argument is, the part
of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah which is the writing, its קדושה
kedusha is dependent on the writing. Once enough writing— once there's almost
no writing left, less than 85 letters, its קדושה kedusha goes away
and even the קדושה kedusha of the parchment, it was all dependent
on the writing. But the stuff that was made as part of
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah that was— that it was a part
of it, but it was a part of it because even as
blank parchment, maybe that status exists even just by itself. Even if
it's— yeah, that would be the question. Even if it's torn from
the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah.
All right, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question going to be. Okay,
so okay, so what's the question? So the גמרא Gemara says: ותיפוק
ליה משום ההוא. V'teipokei lei mishum hahu.
Basically it says exactly what Michael said. So I don't get it,
back to the story of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah with fewer
than 85 letters. Why not save it because of the margin on
the top and the margin on the bottom and the margin— and
the margin between the lines? Who cares if it has less than
85 letters? You still have all the margins that were there that
were blank. So if that's a reason to save it, you should
save it. So the גמרא Gemara says: דגייז ושדי. Degayez v'shadi. No,
maybe that was a case where all of that whitespace was cut
away. Of course, if all the whitespace was cut away, you have
like a lot of— you don't have a continuous scroll, right? I
mean you don't have the space between the columns. So it's hard
to imagine the scenario. I mean you don't have the space between
the columns. So it's hard to imagine the scenario. It's pretty clear
that the margins by themselves do not have status, but the גמרא
Gemara is trying to still make a question. So let's take a
look. תא שמע, ta shma, come in here, another ברייתא. Braita. הגליונים,
Ha-gilyonim, this is in ידים, Yadayim, actually it's a משנה, Mishna, the
ברייתא, Braita, it's a משנה Mishna which talks about the טומאה. tumah.
Remember כתבי קודש kitvei kodesh cause טומאה, tumah, so one of the
ways to determine if something has קדושה kedushah of כתבי קודש kitvei
kodesh is to see whether it has טומאה tumah or not. So
it says, הגליונים שלמעלה ושלמטה, ha-gilyonim she-m'ala u'she-m'ata, the margins above and
below, שבין פרשה לפרשה, she-bein parshah l'parshah, between the פרשיות, parshiyot, שבין
דף לדף, she-bein daf l'daf, between the columns, שבתחילת הספר ובסוף הספר,
she-bit-chilat ha-sefer u'be-sof ha-sefer,
at the beginning of the whole ספר, sefer, at the end of
the ספר, sefer, מטמאין את הידים. metame'in et ha-yadayim. Even if you
just touch the margins, you don't touch the part where writing is
on, it causes טומאה. tumah. So you see they have קדושה. kedushah.
So that's an easy answer. The גמרא Gemara says דילמא אגב ספר
תורה שאני, dilma agav sefer torah shani, that's because they're currently attached
to a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So if the whole ספר תורה
Sefer Torah has קדושה, kedushah, the margins have קדושה kedushah as well.
Again, it does not prove the status of the margins by themselves.
תא שמע, ta shma, come in
here, הגליונים וספרי מינים, ha-gilyonim v'sifrei minim, that's a very
interesting juxtaposition which I'll get back to in a minute. But the
margins and the books of the heretics. Now what does it mean
אין מצילין אותם מפני הדליקה? ein matilin otam mi-p'nei ha-deleikah? You do
not save them from the fire. Now why would I even think
to save a book of a heretic from the fire?
So, a book a heretic wrote as opposed to books of heretics,
not like a radical book, but if a heretic wrote a ספר
תורה Sefer Torah maybe.
Yeah, so that's true. So ספרי מינים sifrei minim could mean one
of two things. תוספות Tosafot assumes here it means a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah that was written by a מין. min. Okay, and that's
also the discussion in גיטין, Gittin, if a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
is written by a מין min what do you do with it?
Because we assume that they had—well, okay, the question is how much
of a מין min is a מין. min. I mean, it might
just
mean—so anyway, but you know there's positions in גיטין Gittin that you
would actually actively go ahead and burn a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
written by a
מין, min, which has questions about whatever. So that raises very interesting
questions about, as you could imagine, some people ask certain הלכה למעשה
halakhah l'ma'aseh questions about certain types of literature nowadays, which I'm going
to just bracket for the moment. Anyway, sorry. So, okay, הגליונים וספרי
מינים אין מצילין מפני הדליקה. ha-gilyonim v'sifrei minim ein matilin mi-p'nei ha-deleikah.
So
those—so anyway, one is a ספר תורה Sefer Torah written by a
מין. min. The other possibility is it's an actual book of a
מין min but it has פסוקים pesukim in it. And I'll get
back and unpack that in a minute. Okay, אין מצילין אותם מפני
הדליקה, ein matilin otam mi-p'nei ha-deleikah, you do not save them. אלא
נשרפין במקומן, ela nisrafin bi-m'koman, you let them be burnt in their
place. הן ואזכרותיהן, hen v'hazkaroteihen, they and even the names of Gods—of
God that is in them. Okay, so מאי לאו, mai lav, doesn't
it mean גליונים דספר תורה, gilyonim d'sefer torah, right? The margins of
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and ספרי מינים? sifrei minim? What a
bizarre juxtaposition unless ספרי מינים sifrei minim means a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah written by a מין. min. So at least we're talking about
within the world of ספרי תורה. sifrei torah. The margins, something written
by a מין, min, so okay, although radically different, at least they're
related to a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So you see it says
you let the גליונים gilyonim burn. So גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
no, גליונים דספרי מינים. gilyonim d'sifrei minim. The actual margins of the
books of the מינים minim or of the ספרי תורה. sifrei torah.
So the גמרא Gemara says I don't get it, השתא ספרי מינים
גופייהו אין מצילין, hashta sifrei minim gufaihu ein matilin, if the very
books themselves or the ספרי תורה sifrei torah themselves you don't save,
גליונים מיבעיא? gilyonim miba'ya? Would there be any question that you don't
save the margins? הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's how you read it.
וספרי מינים, v'sifrei minim, or the ספרי תורה sifrei torah let's read
it that way of the מינים, minim, הרי הן כגליונים, harei hein
k'gilyonim, they are just like
גליונים, gilyonim, but meaning like normal white parchment, unused parchment. ספר תורה
Sefer Torah written by a מין min is no different than like
unused parchment and therefore you can let it burn. So there's really
not a הלכה halakhah about letting the גליונים gilyonim burn. So again,
all of the evidence that we've had is that the margins do
not have status by themselves. They may have status to combine with
something that counts as a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but not by
themselves. And I mean this last one seems to say explicitly you
let it burn, but the גמרא Gemara keeps on trying to get
out of it in order to leave it as a live question.
But again, all of the evidence seems to be that the גליונים
gilyonim do not have status by itself.
At this point, let it burn because it was a גליון gilyon
of a מין, min, which we just...
No, well it says the way it reads it is גליונים gilyonim
that
unused parchment is the same as ספרי מינים sifrei minim and you
let it all burn. But it reads גליונים gilyonim not as a
גליון gilyon of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but סתם stam unused
parchment. Not unused parchment of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, not the
margins of a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. It has—it's a very weak
read of that word in order to get out of it. Now
this issue about ספרי מינים sifrei minim
and the גליונים gilyonim is interesting. And I'm going to tell you
that now and we'll see more about this later about what this
word גליונים gilyonim could mean because although it was introduced by a
whole discussion about a גליון gilyon of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
okay, and the word in the משנה Mishna ידים Yadayim is also
what is this,
הגליונים שלמעלה ושלמטה, ha-gilyonim she-m'ala u'she-m'ata, גליון gilyon of a ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. In the ברייתא Braita where it speaks about גליונים, gilyonim,
it says גליונים וספרי מינים. gilyonim v'sifrei minim. It doesn't have any
context of a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. And a number of scholars
including Professor Saul Lieberman believe that the word גליונים gilyonim in this—
The context of ספרי מינים minim, *sifrei minim* does not have anything
to do with the of the other use of the word גיליון
gilyon, *gilyon*, which means margins, because we are going to see at
the bottom of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that actually there was a
little play on words regarding גיליון *gilyon*. Let me just see if
I can jump you to that.
Hold on.
Okay, we'll find it in a minute. Anyway, there's going to be
a little bit play on words, or maybe the next time. Anyway,
a little play on words which is going to be not גיליונים
gilyonim *gilyonim*, but עון גיליון *Avon Gilyon*. Does that ring any bell
for anybody? עון גיליון *Avon Gilyon*.
Evangelion. Evangelicals, right! So, right is the Greek for for like good
report, which is what evangelical means, or whatever
Evangelion, I don't even know how to pronounce it.
Second to last line...
Oh, there it is.
Second to last line. You know what? That's why I couldn't find
it. It's taken it was edited out. Right, so I knew because
I was using a different edition yesterday. Oh wow. Okay, so anyway,
right. So you want to give that to me? Right. So at
the bottom it says, yeah, you don't it's in the דקדוקי סופרים
*Dikdukei Sofrim*, right? I don't know if it's in the Artscroll. Right,
it says like this, it says רבי מאיר הוי קרי ליה און
גיליון, רבי יוחנן הוי קרי ליה עון גיליון *Rabbi Meir havei karei
lei Aven Gilyon, Rabbi Yochanan havei karei lei Avon Gilyon*. Okay, so
anyway, so it could mean that the גיליונים *gilyonim* here is actually
the gospels. Gospel, right, is the same is basically the English translation
of good report, right? So the גיליונים *gilyonim* and the other books
of the מינים *minim*, because as I'm always telling you, מינים *minim*
very often means Jewish Christians. So basically the gospels and the other
books of the Jewish Christians. And now we understand why it could
be ספר תורה Sefer Torahs, של מינים *sefer Torah shel minim*. It
could also be that's why by the way maybe you have these
harsh statements. Don't, you want to again make very clear the line
between Jews and Jewish Christians and don't, you know, as we're going
to see in a minute, especially because they're so close, it could
actually be more of a pernicious threat. So therefore you have to
treat even a ספר תורה Torah *sefer Torah* written by them very
harshly. Let it burn, or maybe actively burn it, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* in גיטין *Gittin*. But also it could just mean other books
of the other books of their scripture. Now, their scripture very often
quotes, you know, our scripture, and very often has God's name in
it. So then the question is what do you do with it?
If it's quoting, you know, it has פסוקים psukim *psukim* in it,
it has God's name in it, so you let it burn. Okay,
so that is that is again not the way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* here just read the word of גיליון *gilyon*, but that quite
possibly is what the original meaning of that is and we'll see
that as we continue a little bit. So that's the point of
letting those burn.
So according to this position you just said, the ספרי מינים *sifrei
minim* would still be a ספר תורה Torah *sefer Torah*, right?
And גיליון *gilyon* would just be the gospels. Not necessarily. Could be
the other books. Gospel's only part of their scripture. Okay, so now
continues.
But what if they wrote like ישעיהו *Yeshayahu*, right?
No. Oh, well, no. So that is what's clearly discussed in גיטין
*Gittin*. They actually wrote a ספר תורה Torah *sefer Torah*. That could
be what it means here. That's what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* assumes it
means here. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: גופא
*Gufa*.
Let's let's look at what we quoted before. הגיליונים וספרי מינים *Hagilyonim
v'sifrei minim*, the gilyonim and the books of the minim, אין מצילין
אותם מפני הדליקה *ein matzilin otam mipnei hadleika*, you don't save them.
רבי יוסי אומר *Rabbi Yose omer*, בחול *bechol*, if it's a weekday,
then קודר את האזכרות שבהן וגונזן *koder et ha'azkarot shebahen v'gonzan*. What
you do is like this because he wants you to destroy them,
but you still have God's name, so it's one thing to let
them burn. So he says in the weekday you cut out the
names of God that are in it and put those into גניזה
*gniza*, bury those, והשאר שורפן *v'hashar sorfan*, then take the rest and
burn it. Okay, so you are actively burning it, but first removing
God's name on a weekday. אמר רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon's *Amar Rabbi
Tarfon*, says Rabbi Tarfon, Rabbi Tarfon was a big opponent of Christianity
and, you know, which we see in other stories. So and here's
what he says: אקפח akappeach את בני *ekapeiach et banai*, I will
like it's like
I don't even know how to
translate that. It's an idiom. It's like what does not smash but
whatever, anyway. How
did
they translate it?
Charlie, what do they say there?
What does the English say? Charlie, you see the English?
Bury my children. All right.
So אקפח *ekapeiach* is bury?
Yeah, there's different meanings. It's an idiomatic expression. But anyway, like it's
basically like on the life of my sons. It's like a type
of an oath. Okay. Life is like ראובן *Reuven*-ish. Right. Okay. Right.
Anyway. Okay. שאם יבאו לידי *she'im yavo'u leyadai*, if these books were
to ever come into my hand, שאני אשרוף אותם ואזכרות שבהן *she'ani
esrof otam v'hazkarot shebahen*, I would burn them and the names of
God that are in them. שאפילו השם כתוב בהן *she'afilu hashem katuv
bahen*, it's written by them, it doesn't have any קדושה *kedusha*, it's
just letters, it doesn't have any קדושה *kedusha*. שאפילו *she'afilu* and here's
also why, because of the threat that they represent. שאפילו אדם רודף
אחריו להרגו ונחש רץ להכישו *she'afilu adam rodef acharav lehorgo v'nachash ratz
lehachisho*, even if a person is running after you to kill you
or snake running after you and trying to bite you, נכנס לבית
עבודה זרה ואין נכנס לבתיהן של אלו *nichnas l'veit avoda zara v'ein
nichnas l'vateihen shel elu*, I would sooner enter into a house of
idolatry
rather than going into a house of these, meaning of these מינים
*minim*. מינים of, no, a Jewish Christians. No, if it was really
a separate, it was a Gentile Christian, that'd be different, but it's
the Jewish Christians which represent a particular threat. Okay, שהללו shehallalu מכירים
וכופרים, makkirim vekofrim, they, the מינים, know God and rebel against Him,
והללו אינם מכירים וכופרים, vehallalu einam makkirim vekofrim, but the others don't
even know. They're completely different. Meaning the threat that is closer to
you, right, is the more pernicious threat. They have the same discourses
we do, they come from the same background, you know, they started
off as Jews. So it's not just that what they did was
worse. They started as Jews and then they left and that's a
worse sin. It's that they represent a greater threat to people that
are currently, you know, you know, Jewish and not following Christianity. So
therefore you have to be extremely, sort of, you know, you know,
vigorous in your opposition to them because of the threat that they
represent. Charlie had a question?
Yeah, המכירים וכופרים. hamakkirim vekofrim. It doesn't say what they're כופר kofer
about.
Yeah, so presumably they כופר kofer about the fact that the, you
know, who God gave the תורה Torah to, or they כופר kofer
about the fact about the nature of God and the holy aspects
of the Trinity.
They כופר kofer about one particular מצוה. mitzvah. I mean, there're a
lot of things you can be a כופר kofer about according to
some people. Right. Right.
Yeah, it's not clear. But the point is is that these are
people, you know, the threat from within is always greater than the
threat from without. That's the point here. And I should say that
this גמרא as well as, you know, as well as the גמראות
Gemarot we're going to see in a bit, are very important in
terms of being used in conversations about interacting with, you know, with
other religions, interacting with members of other denominations. Some of this stuff
is very often brought in in some of that, you know, discussion
about attitudes towards these types of things.
Yes. So this, he, it sounds like he's, you know, coming down
really hard on one side. I don't know if he's being a
little bit overdramatic on it. Is this an actual הלכה? halacha? Like
let's say, for instance, in Israel, there are whole bunch of Jewish
Christians. Right. So that's what I said. No, no, but another question.
If you're an Orthodox Jew, are you not allowed to employ these
people or is it just going to their church?
No, no, no. It doesn't mean you can't, you can't talk to
them or have them in your house. It means specifically going into
the place where they gather, their church or whatever it is, or
their house of worship because then you're sort of being going into
the lion's den. You know, we'll see in a minute.
Or having them work in your store.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, but even within that question, look, when הרב משה
פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein deals with issues about, you know, can I
teach in a Hebrew school that's in a, that's in a, what
do you call it, that's in a Conservative synagogue? Right? Or these
types of issues, you know, he brings up these types of גמראות.
Gemarot. So again, how exactly you learn, you know, A, do you
adopt רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon approach and B, to what do you
apply that approach? Where do you think that there's a clear and
present threat? Like it's one thing when, you know, when Christianity is
just starting and Jews are breaking off and Jews are, you know,
being sort of, you know, and some Jews are actually following that.
That's one thing about the type of threat that it represents. It's
a quite other thing, you know, at a different stage of history.
So, you know, so this is a question about how, you know,
about, first of all, there are different opinions. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
already רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon. is not the other, and also how
do you apply it, how do you do it in what circumstances?
But these גמראות, Gemarot, I understand. But these גמראות Gemarot are, it's
more about attitude than פסק psak per se, although here it does
translate into פסק psak about even burning the שם השם. Shem Hashem.
Yes, Charlie.
I know numerous Jews who have been told that they should take
jobs teaching in Conservative Reform, right, because as long as they can
teach what they want to teach.
Exactly, exactly. So there's and it all so so much of this
depends on the context, you know, right, exactly.
And I just, my Rav was פוסק posek for me yesterday, last
week, that I can and maybe even should attend a בת מצוה
Bat Mitzvah of a close friend, of the daughter of a close
friend in a Conservative synagogue, which actually surprised me.
Okay, there you go.
Yeah, I'm wondering if this custom of sitting שבעה shiva for children
who intermarry may come from this. Saying I'd rather kill, I'd rather
bury my children. Uh-huh. That's interesting.
I mean, he uses the phrase bury my children, actually as I
was just sort of looked back because it's quoted earlier way at
the beginning in י"ז. yud-zayin. A רש"י Rashi there just says that
אקפח means bury, or cut down or bury, I mean not literally
bury, cut down. But there it was in a much different context.
He was just saying it about some הלכה halacha about טומאה וטהרה
tumah vetaharah and he says, I'll bury my kids if it's not
true that this was a mistake. You know, that was רבי טרפון.
Rabbi Tarfon So he used that, yeah. So he'd kill his kids?
Yeah, all right. Anyway, you know, it's sort of like on the
life of my kids. Anyway, so now we continue. Okay, ועליהם הכתוב
אומר, ve'aleihem hakatuv omer, and regarding them the verse says, ואחר הדלת
והמזוזה שמת זכרונך, ve'achar hadelet vehamazuza sampt zichronech, behind the door and
the מזוזה, mezuzah, the lintel, they have placed your, what? Lintel. Lintel.
I'm sorry, about lentil is a bean. Lintel, they have placed your,
you know, the memory of you, meaning that they knew you, it's
not that they never knew you, but they threw you behind their
back. אמר רבי ישמעאל קל וחומר, Amar Rabbi Yishmael kal vachomer, it's
a קל וחומר. ומה לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו אמרה תורה שמי
kal vachomer uma la'asot shalom bein ish leishto amra Torah shemi. that
you would burn, he agrees that you would burn the actual ספרים
sefarim themselves with God's name in them. קל וחומר kal vachomer. ומה
לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו אמרה תורה שמי. Uma la'asot shalom bein
ish leishto amra Torah shemi שמי שנכתב בקדושה ימחה על המים shemi
shenichtav b'kedusha yemacheh al hamayim for the סוטה, Sotah, in or for
the just sake of creating peace between husband and wife, the תורה
Torah says you can scrape off my name that was written with
sanctity, scrape it into the
water. הללו, Halalu, these
people, שנתנו קנאה ואיבה ותחרות, shenatnu kinah v'eivah v'tachrus, they make, you
know, jealousy and enmity and competition בין ישראל לאביהם שבשמיים bein Yisrael
l'avihem shebashamayim between Israel and their God in heaven, על אחת כמה
וכמה, al achas kama v'kama, how much more so should you destroy
the name in order to remove, you know, the evil that is
created or whatever the enmity is there then. Right, exactly. I would
say though the, you know, Saul Lieberman on his commentary in the
תוספתא, Tosefta, this from a תוספתא, Tosefta, says that maybe the additional
point that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is making is שמי שנכתב בקדושה.
shemi shenichtav b'kedusha. That he's even saying, even it's not even that
we just claim that they're not thinking about God when they write
שם השם. Shem Hashem. Even if they're thinking about God, it doesn't
matter, even if the name is written בקדושה, bikdusha, you would go
ahead and destroy it because of, you know, how the, because of
the threat that this represents. Okay, על אחת כמה
וכמה,
al achas
kama v'kama, how much more so. ועליהם אמר דוד, V'aleihem amar David,
regarding them David said, הלא משנאיך השם אשנא ובתקוממיך אתקוטט. Halo mesanecha
Hashem esnah uviskomimecha eskotat. Behold God, isn't it your enemies I will
hate and those that rise up against you I will fight? תכלית
שנאה שנאתים, Tachlis sinah senasim, right, the ultimate hatred I have hated
them, לאויבים היו לי, l'oyvim hayu li, they were enemies to me.
וכשם שאין מצילין אותם מפני הדליקה, Ucheshem she-ein matzilin osam mipnei hadleika,
the same way you don't save them from the fire, כך אין
מצילין אותם לא מן המפולת ולא מן המים ולא מדבר המאבדן. kach
ein matzilin osam lo min hamapoles v'lo min hamayim v'lo midavar hame'avdan.
You don't save them from water or a building that falls on
them or anything that destroys them, which is pretty obvious, you just
saw me I'm supposed to burn them. So it could be that
this is going back to the first opinion that doesn't say actively
burn them, says just don't save them. And it's saying and the
point about not saving them on שבת, Shabbat, this is the way
תוספות Tosafot reads them, is not just because of a concern you'll
put out a fire. Even if it's not a fire, we're not
concerned
of any מלאכה, melacha, don't save them because look, even in the
weekday the most, you know, the most lenient or whatever you would
call it opinion is cut out the name of God and still
actively burn it. So here you see really this very powerful, you
know, approach about seeing these as tremendous threats. And of course if
they are, you know, the Christian testament, then you understand it's not
just because it comes from people who are, you know, who are
seen as threatening the faith of the faithful and so on, but
it's also the very testaments themselves are very much speaking in a
language that Jews understand. You know, I mean it's using a lot
of, I mean certainly the Gospels is using a lot of, you
know, the type of quoting of verses and, you know, using of
almost a rabbinic type of a language. Sometimes what Jesus is saying
is sort of a very, you know, draws on like a whole
rabbinic discourse. So you really understand like the threat that these represent.
These discussions are used sometimes nowadays. Thankfully, I would say it's very
rare that people bring up these גמרות Gemorot in the context of
like actual Christian testaments that, you know, that think that this would
be relevant. I mean again, the threat has shifted. But the question
where this does come up is about the Jews for Jesus literature.
Okay? And some people very much say yeah, you should totally burn
it, it doesn't matter if they quote פסוקים or anything, just gotta
totally destroy it. Yeah.
Yeah. I bought the Jewish New Testament that some Jewish scholars, academics
put together
with commentary.
Did it come with a book of matches attached to it?
Yeah. I mean I was gonna, I didn't ask the שאלות she'elot
whether whether I should buy it and burn it, but even to
me it was astonishing how many, how deeply they are citing and
comparing and making it look like it is a Jewish text.
Right, there's a lot of patterning it after the Jewish stories, there's
a lot of direct engagement with that quoting of verses.
It's absolutely astonishing.
And you understand in the context of trying to convince Jews to
become Christians and followers of Jesus. I can see how it
would have worked back in the day. It is an amazing thing
to me, so it doesn't work very well today.
Well, today how many people read any text, you know, any scripture
seriously? So yes, this... Wait, wait, תוספות Tosfos says?
You mean רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael part
of the עשרה הרוגי מלכות? asara harugei malchus?
I believe.
Yes.
Yes, רבי טרפון as well? No. They were both around the year
like 70, I mean they were after the חורבן, Churban, רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Ishmael, I mean you know, this was רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
of יבנה, Yavne, so oh, this is רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, not
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. But they were targeted because of their views?
Right, yeah. If
they were part of the עשרה...
asara... Oh, that's interesting. That's an interesting question. Right, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael was more the contemporary of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that was
like 130. Yeah, I don't know, could be. I have no idea
about that's a very good question.
But we didn't exactly, even in ספר תורה, Torah. we didn't fully
explore at least in this משנה Mishnah what we're saving too. I
mean it doesn't, you know, doesn't רש"י Rashi say מבוי שאינו מפולש?
m'avoy she'eino mefulash?
We're not, don't worry about that, we're getting there. Okay. I was
very worried about the bottom of my הלכה halacha there. Okay, anyway,
the גמרא continues now.
Okay. So it says like this.
Okay. ואימא מאן דעביד *ve'eima mad d'avid* oh I just read that.
Okay וכשם ש *U'keshaim she* we just did that. Okay בעי מיניה
*Ba'ei minei* יוסף בר חנין *Yosef bar Chanin* מרבי אבהו *mei'Rabbi Abbahu*.
So יוסף בר חנין *Yosef bar Chanin* asked רבי אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu*
הני ספרי דבי אבידן *hanei sifrei devei Avidan* and so he's talked
about books of המינים *ha'Minim* and we've talked about, you know, ספרי
תורה Torah *Sifrei Torah* that are written or things written other languages
and do they retain their קדושה *kedusha*? How about the books of
בי אבידן Bei Abidan, *Bei Avidan*? Right? I'll discuss I'll talk about
that in a minute. מציל אותם מפני הדליקה או אין מציל אותם
*matzil osam mipnei ha'dleika o ein matzil osam*? Would you or would
you or would you not save them from the דליקה *dleika*? אין
ולאו ורפיא בידיה *In velav v'rafya b'yadei*. He says, "Yes, no," he
wasn't sure. It was weak in his hands. He would be vacillating.
He wouldn't really know how to פסקן *pasken* about that. Okay, now
what is this בי אבידן Bei Abidan. *Bei Avidan*? So if you
look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, very interesting, he says, here's רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*, בי אבידן Bei Abidan, *Bei Avidan*, the first of the wide
lines at the end, ספרים שכתבו להם מינים להתווכח עם ישראל *sefarim
she'katvu lahem Minim le'hitvake'ach im Yisrael*, that it was books used for
for like a disputations. מקום שמתווכח קרי ליה בי אבידן *makom she'mitvake'ach
kari lei Bei Avidan* and they would call it the house of
בי אבידן *Bei Avidan*. רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* has a longer explanation.
If you look on the left margin about ten lines down, ספרי
*sifrei* is a bold word at the end of a long line.
He says, ספרי דבי אבידן *sifrei devei Avidan*, חצר ידועה *chatzar yedu'a*,
it was a known courtyard, ויש בה ספרי חכמות *v'yesh bah sifrei
chochmos* מכל אומה *mi'kol uma*, they had, you know, the it was
like the library of Alexandria. They had, you know, the wisdom literature
of all the nations. ויש בהם ספרי תורה Torah. נביאים Nevi'im? וכתובים
*v'yesh bahem Sifrei Torah Nevi'im u'Kesuvim* כתובים Ketuvim. בלשון הקודש *kesuvim b'Lashon
HaKodesh*. So among the literature, the wisdom literature of all the nations,
they also had the, you know, ספרי תורה *Sifrei Torah* and they
had other they had the תנ"ך *Tanakh*. Okay. ומי כתבה או ישראל
או זוטם *umi kesavah o Yisrael o zutam*? And people would have
it to access it in order to debate. ומפני שאינו ידוע מי
כתבה או ישראל או זוטם *u'mipnei she'eino yadu'a mi kesavah o Yisrael
o zutam*, they don't know who wrote these books. Were they written
by a Jew and therefore they have קדושה *kedusha* or not written?
Okay, אמרו על רבי אבהו *amru al Rabbi Abbahu*. Okay, and then
he goes on. שהיה הדבר רפיא בידו להורות עליהם להצילן או לא
*she'hayah ha'davar rafya b'yado le'haros aleihem le'hatzilan o lo*. He didn't know.
Okay. And then he goes on and says וזהו בי אבידן שהיו
מתקבצים שם חכמים ונבונים *v'zehu Bei Avidan she'hayu mitkabtzim sham chachamim v'nevonim*,
all like all the wise people, the philosophers would gather there, מכל
אומה *mi'kol uma*, ונושאים ונותנים בדברי חכמה *v'nos'im v'nos'nim b'divrei chochma*, and
they would actually and it doesn't so much from him sound as
much as רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* להתווכח *le'hitvake'ach*, like it was a disputation.
It sounds more like it was almost like a library, like a
right, some type of scholarly endeavor. So this is בי אבידן *Bei
Avidan*. So they would have in them things that would have פסוקים
*psukim* in them, maybe actual even ספרי תורה *Sifrei Torah*. And the
question would be again, who wrote them? Were they written by Jews,
not Jews, yes מינים *Minim*, not מינים *Minim*? What would you save
them from the דליקה *dleika*? And they did not know. Okay, it
does not sound like the question is would you save the book
of, you know, Plato or Aristotle? They're talking about ספרים *sefarim* that
are have some, you know, are either ספרי תורה *Sifrei Torah*, at
least have פסוקים *psukim* and so on. All right. So now it
says, now we're going to have a now we're going to have
an interesting discussion about who participated in this בי אבידן *Bei Avidan*
or not.
I have seen, by the way, that some try to connect this
בי אבידן *Bei Avidan* with the with the
is it called the Odeum which is some type of a Greek,
like a gathering place again which would be used for philosophical disputations.
So I think like something that sometimes serves as a theater, but
sometimes used for philosophical disputations. Anyway, there's some attempt to connect it
with the Greek word. Some also say that it could be a
play on words, like like from the word like אבד *avad*, you
know, it should be destroyed or whatever something critical. Although you see
the גמרא *Gemara* is not so clearly critical about it. And now
we're going to have some discussion around it. Okay, so it says
like this. רב לא אזיל לבי אבידן *Rav lo azil l'Bei Avidan*.
רב *Rav* would not go to the house of בי אבידן *Bei
Avidan*. וכל שכן לבי נצרפי *v'chol she'ken l'Bei Netzarphei*, and certainly to
the house of נצרפי *Netzarphei*. Now what's house of נצרפי *Netzarphei*? So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that was a real בית עבודה זרה *beis
avodah zarah*.
So right, obviously he wouldn't go.
So some say again what it is is a play or it
might be alluding to the word נוצרי *Notzri*, exactly. And maybe again
this is a place where where Christians would gather, not a church
presumably then it would be obvious, but maybe again a place of
discussion.
And נוצרי *Notzri* as opposed to מין min. *min* means a Gentile
Christian. Okay. But again here, you know, it seems that there were
opportunities for religious discussion. Would people participate in it or not?
Some say this is a Christian church.
A Christian church, actually. Okay, that's going to be interesting. Anyway, so
anyway, so I mean, yeah, there's a lot of speculation around that.
But this as before the discussion was what types of things do
you have to go ahead and burn and what types of places
can you go into in terms of like other denominations and whatever
this גמרא *Gemara* is very important for discussion about interreligious dialogue, right?
To what degree do you look at some of the attitudes expressed
here as significant for that? So let's take a look. So רב
*Rav* would not go to either. שמואל Shmuel לבי נצרפי לא אזיל
*Shmuel l'Bei Netzarphei lo azil*. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* would not go to
בי נצרפי *Bei Netzarphei* because that was like, you know, the other
religion and maybe again more threatening or whatever he or maybe more
threatening to him personally, his own safety. We'll see about that. לבי
אבידן אזיל *L'Bei Avidan azil*. He'd be willing to go to בי
אבידן *Bei Avidan* which is more, you know, just larger intellectual philosophical
discussion. אמרו ליה לרבא *Amru lei l'Rava*. They said to רבא *Rava*,
whoever the they. they is, מאי טעמא לא אתית לבי אבידן? Hey,
you know, we had that great, we had that great conference the
other day in בי אבידן, why didn't you go? אמר להו דיקלא
פלניא איכא באורחא. Amar lehu: dikla planya ika be-urcha. There was a
certain palm tree got in the way, you know whatever my car
broke down, וקשי לי, ve-kashi li, it was difficult for me. So
they said, no, no problem, next time נעקרי דקלי, na'akrei diklei, we'll
just uproot it. Hey, if that's the problem, no problem, we'll call
you a car service. So says, קשי לי, kashi li, no, that'd
be difficult, I don't want there to be an uprooted tree over
there. Fine. Okay, we get the idea. He'd make excuses which also
shows that there was pressure to go, pressure from, you know, social
pressure, pressure from the non-Jews who were part of it.
There was also a פסק psak that no one should go.
Right, this is a question about expressing of attitudes. Certainly some people
would participate. מר בר רב יוסף אמר אנא מנייהו. Mar bar Rav
Yosef amar ana minaihu.
I am from among them, meaning, you know, אנא ולא מסתפינא מנייהו,
ana v'lo mistafina minaihu,
and I'm not afraid of them, meaning I'm not because apparently now
that meant either, you know, this was Rav Soloveitchik was very concerned
about inter-religious dialogue because he felt that just the nature of the
discourse would create a certain sense of reciprocity and you'd feel a
pressure to sort of make concessions that really were not true to
your own, you know, faith and your own convictions. So what does
it mean to be afraid of them? Does it mean to be
afraid in terms of being feeling a pressure to say things that
I don't really believe in? Is that or does it mean just
afraid for your own personal safety? You know, that if you actually
do say what you believe in, like when the רמב"ן Ramban had
a disputation at, you know, the disputation at Barcelona, right?
He made the mistake of winning!
He made the mistake of winning, and that's when he ended with
him making עליה aliyah because he couldn't
stay stay too long after he won. But okay, so maybe you're
afraid to actually say what you do believe because then that's risking
your personal security.
Could also be that, oh here's something that will change my maybe.
I mean that was more like the first thing I was saying,
or make me say something I really don't want to say. זימנא
חדא אזל, zimna chada azal, one time he went, בעו לסכוניה, ba'u
l'sakunei, and they wanted to endanger him, meaning that actually does sound
like physically, right? Anyway, so you see the issue here about people
that would or wouldn't participate but the point is it has to
be treated very carefully because of not only personal safety but other
types other concerns about, you know, religious maintaining one's religious integrity.
But I have a question about the even the בי אבידן. So
if they were going to this בי אבידן, I guess this maybe
disagrees with the other things that you said that you can't do
like let's say חכמה יוונית, chochma yevanit, you know, you gotta do
it at a time that's not day, not night.
But we'll discuss it when we get to חכמה יוונית. chochma yevanit.
That's the גמרא where חכמה יוונית chochma yevanit could have a very
limited scope. All right, and this is by the way where the
line comes in about, you know, Rav would call it עוון גיליון
avon gilyon which is like the nonsense of gilyon, and Shmuel would
call it עוון avon with an עין ayin גיליון, the sin of
gilyon, but that again is this play on the word of, you
know, about Evangelion whatever, I don't even know how to pronounce it,
anyway, which is again the gospel which is presumably the גיליונים referred
to before.
רבי מאיר ורבי יוחנן. Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yochanan.
Rabbi Meir, Rabbi Yochanan. Thank you. Okay, so אימא שלום דביתהו דרבי
אליעזר אחותו דרבן גמליאל. Ima Shalom d'veiseihu d'Rabbi Eliezer achoso d'Rabban Gamliel.
Ima Shalom, who makes more sense because it's ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Ima Shalom, the wife of Rabbi Eliezer, the sister of Rabban Gamliel.
So this is roughly at the end of the first century.
הוה ההוא פילוסופא. Hava hahu filosofa. There was a certain philosopher. Now
what's a פילוסופא? filosofa? So Rashi says מין. If you look at
Tosafos, פילוסופא, filosofa, it says מין כדפירוש בקונטרס. min k'defirush b'kuntres. רבינו
שמה Rabbeinu Shamma מיהודי אחד שבא מארץ יון, mi-Yehudi echad she-ba me-Eretz
Yavan, a certain Jew that came from Greece, ואמר, v'amar, and said
בלשון יון, bi-lshon Yavan, in Greek, פילוסופא filosofa הוא דוס החכמה, hu
dost hachochma, the lover of wisdom. Philos, Sophia, filosofa, lover of wisdom.
Okay, so anyway, so very interesting getting it from somebody who actually
knows Greek. Okay, so anyway, there was a certain פילוסופא filosofa בשיבבותיה
be-shivevusei in their neighborhood, דהוה שקיל שמא דלא מקבל שוחדא. de-hava shakil
sh'ma d'lo m'kabel shochda. He had this reputation that he was so
honest, he would never accept a bribe, he would always just speak
the truth. הוה שמא. Hava sh'ma. שקיל שמא, shakil sh'ma, he had
a שם טוב, shem tov, he had a good he had a
name, a reputation. בעו לאחוכי ביה. Ba'u l'achochei bei.
They wanted to mock him, they wanted to like show him up.
אעיילה שרגא דדהבא, A'ayala shraga de-dahava, so she gave him sent him
like a gold candle, like a candelabrum, the אימא שלום. Ima Shalom.
ואזלו לקמיה, v'azlu l'kamei, and then went in front of him. אמרה
ליה, Amra lei, she said to him, בעינא דניפלגי לי בנכסי דבי
נשי. Be'ina d'niflagi li b'nichsei d'vei nashi. I want you to give
me a portion of the inheritance of the mother's house, of my
mother's house, an inheritance I got, you know, from from it was
I mean
she and Rabban Gamliel were brother and sister, she said I want
a portion of that inheritance. אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said
to them, to presumably it was Rabban Gamliel, presumably
to Rabban Gamliel and Ima Shalom, he said to them, פלוגו, plugu,
fine, divide it. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so Rabban Gamliel said wait a minute, כתיב לן, kesiv lan, it's
written for us במקום ברא ברתא לא תירות, bi-mkom b'ra barta lo
tirus,
that if there's a son that's around, a daughter doesn't inherit, right?
Even after בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad it's only with no sons. אמר
להו, amar lehu, he said back to them: מן יומא דגליתו מארעכון,
min yoma de-galitu me-arkhon,
from the day that you were exiled from your land, which is,
I mean they lived here at the end of the first century,
so they haven't been exiled too long and presumably רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel is still in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but it means you
as a people have been exiled from your land. אשתרי אורייתא דמשה,
ishtari oraita de-Moshe,
the Torah of Moses has been taken away, ויהיבת ספרא אחרינא, ve-yehibat
sifra achrina, and another book has been given. Okay, so this is
וכתיב ביה, ve-chtiv beh, and it's written there: ברא וברתא כחדא ירתון,
bera ve-barta ke-chada yartun,
that son and daughter inherit equally. Now, it's never, it doesn't say
that anywhere in Christian scripture, not because I'm an expert in Christian
scripture, but because I actually have this book as I said that
talks about, written by a priest, that actually it's a great book,
I've read it, it's like Christianity in the תלמוד Talmud and the
מדרש, Midrash, which discusses all, every single passage and and what?
No, not Strack. Travers?
Travers? I don't know. Anyway, I was going to bring it. Anyway,
and he says, you know, he quotes every single, he's great, he
quotes all these sources and he discusses what the historical context is
and so on. Anyway, he says there's no verse that says this.
But what you do have is, I think it's the line from
Paul about something like "With us there's no Jew and Gentile, no
man, no woman," like everybody is equal, no slave, nor free man,
like Galatians said, everybody is equal. So presumably that's what it was
alluding to. We mentioned עוון גליון avon gilyon earlier.
Yes, what's that?
He quotes עוון גליון. avon gilyon.
Yeah, the עוון גליון avon gilyon we quoted before.
Yeah, and it says your תורה was taken away and there's this
new one, there's this evangelical עוון גליון. avon gilyon.
Oh, so it has עוון גליון avon gilyon here instead of another
book. Oh, that's interesting. Okay, that's good, that's continuing to play on
the עוון גליון avon gilyon that we mentioned before. Okay, very good.
So anyway, all right, so we've been given the Evangelion, we've been
given the Gospels, and this is what it says. ליומא דמחר, le-yoma
de-machar, הדר עייל ליה חמרא לובא. hadar ayeil lei chamra luba.
So then רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel sent him a Libyan donkey as
a bigger bribe. And then they came in front of him the
next day. אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said to them, you
know what? שפילית לסיפא דספרא. shafilit le-seifa de-safra. I looked at the
end of this book, my book. Does it say there עוון גליון?
avon gilyon? Or does it say דספרא? de-safra? עוון גליון. avon gilyon.
Okay, so anyway, I looked at the end, וכתיב ביה, ve-chtiv beh,
and it's written there: אנא לא למיפחת מן אורייתא דמשה אתיתי, ana
lo le-mipchat min oraita de-Moshe ateiti,
I have not come to take away from the תורה of Moses,
ולא לאוסופי על אורייתא דמשה אתיתי, ve-lo le-usufi al oraita de-Moshe ateiti,
and I have not come to add to the תורה of Moses,
right, which is also a saying of Jesus, right? I do not
know. So וכתיב ביה, ve-chtiv beh, oh, so if that's true, וכתיב
ביה במקום ברא ברתא לא תירות, ve-chtiv beh bimkom bera barta lo
teiras, according to your תורה. So it says therefore that in the
place of a son, a daughter doesn't inherit. So now he got
a bigger bribe from רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. אמרה ליה, amra lei,
so she said to him, נהור נהורך כשרגא, nehor nehorach ke-sharga, your
light should shine like a candle, meaning she was alluding to him,
"Hey, what about the bribe I gave you?" Okay. אמר ליה רבן
גמליאל, amar lei Rabban Gamliel, so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said to
her, or to him, אתא חמרא ובטש לשרגא. ata chamra u-batash le-sharga.
I'm sorry, the donkey already came and kicked over your candle.
So as רש"י says, the point was to publicize, make it obvious
to everybody around there that here was a guy who was bribed.
He had this reputation about being so honest, he flips one the
other. It's also a little bit mocking Christianity on the one hand,
you know, it seems like they're coming to supersede the תורה and
with their new scripture, but then Jesus says that he's not coming
to change the תורה. So they're having a nice time, you know,
making fun of all of this, of course, as was pointed out
by Seth. Yeah, not too much in the future where you're going
to have the Hadrianic persecutions.
So you gotta be really careful when you're doing that type of
stuff. All right, let's try to just get to the משנה. mishnah.
ומפני מה אין קורין? u-mipnei mah ein korin? Why do you not
read from these? Now we're totally putting that aside, which was a
lot of fun and fascinating, and we're back to reading from כתובים.
Ketuvim You don't read from כתובים Ketuvim on שבת. Shabbat. So why
not? So אמר רב, amar Rav, because it's ביטול בית המדרש. bittul
beis ha-medrash. אמר רב לא שנו אלא בזמן בית המדרש. amar Rav
lo shanu ella bi-zman beis ha-medrash. That's only at the time of
the בית המדרש, beis ha-medrash, which רש"י says was actually right after
דאווענינג davening before the meal. אבל שלא בזמן בית המדרש, aval she-lo
bi-zman beis ha-medrash, not at that time, קורין, korin, you could read
because you're not keeping people away from the בית המדרש. beis ha-medrash.
ושמואל אמר אפילו שלא בזמן בית המדרש אין קורין, u-Shmuel amar afilu
she-lo bi-zman beis ha-medrash ein korin, even not during the time you're
not allowed to read. איני, eini, is that really true? והא נהרדעא
אתריה דשמואל הוה, ve-ha Nahardea atraih de-Shmuel havah, Nehardea was שמואל's's Shmuel
location, ובנהרדעא פסיק סדרא בכתובים במנחתא דשבתא, u-ve-Nahardea pasik sidra bi-chtuvim be-minchata
de-shabta, and in Nehardea they would read from the כתובים Ketuvim on
מנחה mincha of שבת. Shabbat. Some say it means the הפטרה, haftarah,
interesting that they would do it from כתובים Ketuvim and do it
on שבת Shabbat and do it at מנחה mincha time. Anyway, but
they would read כתובים Ketuvim. at מנחה mincha time, and that's not
the time of the בית המדרש. beis ha-medrash. אלא
אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ella i itmar hachi itmar, if it was
said, here's what was said. אמר רב לא שנו אלא במקום בית
המדרש. amar Rav lo shanu ella bi-makom beis ha-medrash. You're only not
allowed to do it in the בית המדרש beis ha-medrash itself. If
you're there you should be listening to the דרשה, drasha, not reading
the כתובים. Ketuvim By the way, why would they read כתובים Ketuvim
more than נביאים? Nevi'im I raised that issue last time since נביאים
have all this good narrative in it. It could be that the
parts of the כתובים ksuvim were in ארמית, Aramaic, like דניאל Daniel
and עזרא ונחמיה, Ezra ve-Nechemiah, so everybody knew ארמית, Aramaic, not everybody
knew עברית. Hebrew. So that maybe had something to do with it.
Anyway, אבל שלא במקום בית המדרש, aval she-lo bi-makom beis ha-medrash, if
you're not in the בית המדרש beis ha-medrash itself, קורין, korin, you're
allowed to read. ושמואל אמר בין במקום בית המדרש בין שלא במקום
בית המדרש. u-Shmuel amar bein bi-makom beis ha-medrash bein she-lo bi-makom beis
ha-medrash. whether you're in the בית המדרש base medrash or not, בזמן
בית המדרש אין קורין, bizman base medrash ein korin, if it's the
time of the בית המדרש base medrash then you shouldn't be reading.
Yeah, I mean just you know, if you're out of the בית
המדרש base medrash we gotta get you into the בית המדרש base
medrash so you shouldn't be reading you should be coming to the
שיעור, shiur, אין קורין. ein korin. But שלא בזמן בית המדרש shelo
bizman base medrash when it's not that time, קורין korin then you
can read. Then ואזדא שמואל לטעמיה, ve'azda Shmuel l'teimei, that's consistent with
what he says דבי נהרדעא פסקי סידרא דכתובים במנחתא דשבתא. debei Naharda
paskei sidra diksuvim beminchasa d'shabsa. They read from the כתובים ksuvim at
מנחה mincha and שבת shabbos time because that's no longer the time
of the בית המדרש. base medrash. רב אשי אמר לעולם כדאמרן מעיקרא.
Rav Ashi amar l'olam k'da'amran meikara.
It's like we said originally. ושמואל V'shmuel so that שמואל Shmuel says
you don't read it even not during the time, even not of
the בית המדרש. base medrash. So why not? And how about the
fact that in שמואל's Shmuel location they did read? שמואל כרבי נחמיה.
Shmuel k'Rebbi Nechemia. שמואל Shmuel isn't saying his own opinion. His own
opinion is you could read it not during the time of the
בית המדרש. base medrash. And that's what they did in נהרדעא. Naharda.
What he was doing was giving expression to the position of רבי
נחמיה. Rebbi Nechemia. דתניא, Detanya, we turn a ברייתא, braisa, אף על
פי שאמרו כתבי הקודש אין קורין בהן, af al pi she'amru kisvei
hakodesh ein korin bahen, although you can't read the כתבי הקודש, kisvei
hakodesh, אבל שונין בהן ודורשין בהן. aval shonin bahen vedorshin bahen. You
can learn and give דרשות drashos on them. Now what does that
mean? So could mean אין קורין ein korin means you don't do
a ritual reading of it, but that wouldn't fit so well in
the earlier discussion which seems like it's just taking people out of
the בית המדרש base medrash not just ritual. So someone wants to
say it means that you don't read from them בכתב, bichsav, but
you can discuss it בעל פה. ba'al peh. Okay, and you can
have discussions about it בעל פה. ba'al peh. But why read it?
Again, that would be something that I don't know, whatever the social
context is, that would be something that if you let people do
it they'd all be doing that instead of going to the בית
המדרש. base medrash. Okay, נצרך לפסוק, nitzrach lefasuk, if you actually need
to check something then to see a פסוק, pasuk, מביא ורואה בו,
meivi veroeh bo, then you can look up a פסוק. pasuk. But
don't spend time just sitting and reading it like sitting and getting
absorbed in a good book and then you'll be out of the
בית המדרש. base medrash.
Even if not in a בית המדרש base medrash you can't do
it
because No, no, no, this doesn't give you the time. This just
adds the qualification about you can discuss it without reading it. אמר
רבי נחמיה, Amar Rebbi Nechemia, now רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia says, and
this is where שמואל Shmuel what שמואל's saying although שמואל doesn't hold
like רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia but he's saying before, מפני מה אמרו
כתבי הקודש אין קורין בהן, mipnei ma amru kisvei hakodesh ein korin
bahen, why not read them? It's not because it'll take you out
of the בית המדרש. base medrash. Totally different reason. כדי שיאמרו בכתבי
הקודש אין קורין כל שכן בשטרי הדיוטות. kedei sheyomru bekisvei hakodesh ein
korin kol shekein bishtarei hedyotos. People will say, oh if we can't
even read כתובים we certainly can't read secular documents now and newspapers
and whatever. So this is according to that approach it doesn't matter
time of the בית המדרש base medrash not time of the בית
המדרש. base medrash. It's a way to signal to people that you
can't go ahead and read every single thing on שבת. Shabbat. Now
I want to end by saying what constitutes שטרי הדיוטות. shtarei hedyotos.
So if you look at רש"י, רש"י says כגון של חשבונות, kegon
shecheshbonos, which are like you know sort of like accounting documents, very
much business, okay, או אגרות השלוחות למצוא חפצו oh igaros hashulchos limtzo
cheftzo or just you know letters, anything that's type of just you
know secular reading even if it's completely not business related. So תוספות
Tosfos has a whole discussion because תוספות Tosfos says you know we
do read letters and basically if you want a cute thing remember
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam said look here's why we read a letter.
If it's got a if you don't know what's in it then
you could read it because maybe it's a real urgent matter that
has to be attended to on שבת. Shabbos. And if you already
do know what's in it then he says
then he says wait one minute he says I'm just reading תוספות
Tosfos דלא הוי שטרי הדיוטות כיון שאין צריך למאי דכתיב בה. dlo
havei shtarei hedyotos kivein she'ein tzarich lemash d'kasiv beh.
If you already know what's in it then you don't really need
to be reading it. So then it's not really a problem. And
if you don't know what's in it then you have to read
it because maybe it's something urgent that you have to attend to.
Whatever, it's one of those things like the medicine story. But then
I want to read you the end of תוספות Tosfos because the
end of תוספות Tosfos says the following, he says about six lines
from the end of this תוספות וכל שכן, Tosfos v'chol shekein, he
says ומיהו, u'mihu,
so anyway תוספות Tosfos tries to limit the problem to business documents,
other types of literature is okay. And then he says like letters
and other types of things that you're reading for you know for
pleasure, that תוספות Tosfos would say would be okay. ומיהו U'mihu says
תוספות אותן מלחמות הכתובים בלע"ז, osan milchamos haksulvim b'la'az,
reading stories of wars written in the vernacular like we would say
like a good novel or maybe even a history book, נראה לרבנו
יהודה דאסור לעיין בהן. nireh l'Rabbeinu Yehuda de'asur l'ayen bahen.
That you can't read. דלא גרע מהא דתניא פרק שואל כתב שתחת
הצורה והדיוקנאות אסור לקרות בהן בשבת. d'lo gara me'ha d'tanya perek shoel
kesav shetachas hatzura vehadiyoknos asur likros bahen b'Shabbos.
That would be considered completely inappropriate. ואפילו בחול לא ידעתי מי התיר.
ve'afillu bechol lo yadatai mi hitir. Even in the weekday who allowed
you to be reading like novels? דהוי מושב לצים. dehavei moshav leitzim.
So it's quite fascinating when you look this up in שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch in הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos when it talks about reading
business documents and what can you read and can't you read, it
also goes on a similar digression about what types of things you
shouldn't even be reading during the week, specifically points out romances okay
that you shouldn't be reading those because of so anyway, here's an
interesting question about the line of what types of things you can
and cannot read on שבת. Shabbat.